-=圣城家园 CnSCG 荣誉出品=-
Lovebeans 作品
hd.cnscg.com
本字幕由人人影视翻译
1925年
英王乔治五世统治着世界四分之一的人口
他命自己的次子约克公爵
为在伦敦温布利举行的帝国博览会致闭幕词
国王的演讲
You are live in two minutes, Your Royal Highness.
殿下  离您出场还有两分钟
Sir?
殿下
At the microphone, Do your work Sir.
在话筒前讲话就可以了  阁下
I am sure you will be splendid. Just take your time.
我相信您会做得很出色  只要别急
Time to go.
去吧
Good afternoon.
下午好
This is the BBC National Programme and Empire Services
现在是由BBC国家电台及大英帝国电台
taking you to Wembley Stadium
为您直播在温布利体育场举行的
for the Closing Ceremony of the Empire Exhibition.
帝国博览会闭幕式
where His Royal Highness the
约克公爵殿下将在此宣读
Duke of York will read a message from his Father;
来自他父王
His Majesty, King George V.
乔治五世的祝词
58 British Colonies and Dominions have taken part,
五十八个英属殖民地和领地的参加
making this the largest Exhibition staged anywhere in the world.
使之成为全世界最盛大的博览会
Remember Sir, Three flashes;
记住  殿下  指示灯会闪三下
then steady 'red' means you are Live.
然后亮红灯  说明广播开始
Using the new invention of radio,
收音机问世
The Opening Ceremony was the first time...
使国王陛下首次通过无线电
his Majesty the King addressed his subjects on the wireless.
在开幕式上发表了演说
At the close of the first Season,
第一期结束时
The heir to the throne His Royal Highness...
王储威尔士亲王殿下
the Prince of Wales, made his first broadcast.
也发表了首次广播演说
And today, his younger brother His Royal Highness,
今天  他的弟弟
the Duke of York will give his
约克公爵殿下也将首次通过广播
inaugural broadcast to the Nation and the World.
向大英帝国以及全世界致闭幕词
I have received...
我收到了
from his Majesty the...
国王  国
The King...
国王陛下的
1934年
伦敦  皮卡迪利大街145号
Inhale deep into your lungs... Your Royal Highness.
深深吸进肺里  殿下
Relaxes your larynx, does it not?
这能放松您的喉咙  是吧
Cigarette smoking calms the nerves and gives you confidence.
吸烟让您精神放松并给您自信
Now, if Your Highness will be so kind as to open your hand.
殿下  请您张开手
It's Sterilized.
这是消过毒的
One, two, three,
一  二  三
four, five, six, seven.
四  五  六  七
Now, if I may take the liberty,
恕我冒昧
insert them into your mouth.
请把它们含在嘴里
Excuse me, Doctor. What is the purpose of this?
抱歉  医生  请问这样做是为了什么
It is the classic approach, it cured Demosthenes.
这是传统疗法  它治好了德摩斯梯尼(古希腊雄辩家)
That was in Ancient Greece.
那是在古希腊
Has it worked since?
现在还管用吗
Now, if you would be so kind as to read.
现在  请您读一下
"A wealth of words."
这几段话
Fight against those marbles, Your Royal Highness.
克服那些弹珠的阻碍  殿下
Enunciate!
读出来
A little more concentration your Royal Higness.
再专心一点  殿下
I nearly swallowed the bloody things!
我差点吞了这些该死的玩意儿
Thank you so much, Doctor,
谢谢您  医生
it's been most, hmm... interesting.
这非常  有意思
Your highness.
殿下
Insert... marbles!
含  弹珠
He can insert his own bloody marbles.
他自己怎么不含
Tick, tock. Tick, tock.
滴答  滴答
You know, you can't keep doing this, Bertie.
你不能总这样  博迪
I know.
我知道
Promise me. Promise me, no more.
答应我  答应我  治疗到此为止
哈里街
查普曼医生
L·罗格  语言障碍
Hello. Is anyone there?
你好  有人在吗
I'm just in the loo.
我在厕所里
Ah, Mrs.Johnson, there you are.
约翰逊夫人  您来了
I'm sorry, there's no receptionist. I like to keep things simple.
抱歉  我这没前台  我喜欢简单
"Poor and content is rich and rich enough."
"乐而安贫就是富"
- I'm Sorry?  - Shakespeare. How are you?
- 什么  - 莎士比亚说的  您好
How do you do?
您好
Oh, chuffing along.
我近来咳嗽不断
Um, now, this is slightly awkward, but I'm afraid you're late.
这有点棘手  但是  恐怕您迟到了
Yes, I'm afraid I am.
是的  恐怕是的
Where's Mr Johnson?
约翰逊先生呢
Ah... He doesn't know I'm here.
他不知道我来
That's not a promising start.
这个开头可不好
No. No, look,
是  是不好  情形是
my husband has seen everyone to no avail.
我丈夫求医无数  皆无好转
Awefully 'fraid he's given up hope.
恐怕他已经放弃了
He hasn't seen me.
他还没见过我
You're awfully sure of yourself.
你很自信
Well, I'm sure of anyone who wants to be cured.
我对每个期望治好的人都满怀信心
Of course, he wishes to be cured.
当然他想要治好
My husband is um... Well, he's required to speak publicly.
我丈夫  需要在公开场合讲话
Perhaps he should change jobs?
或许他该换个工作
He can't.
没法换
Indentured servitude?
卖身契
Something of that nature. Yes.
差不多
Well we need to have your hubby pop by.
那么  你老公得过来
Uh..Tuesday would be good...
周二可以
He can give me his personal details
他可以跟我说下个人情况
and I'll make a frank appraisal and then, We can take it from there.
我来做个准确评估  然后开始治疗
Doctor, forgive me.
抱歉  医生
I do not have a hubby. We don't pop.
我不称他为老公  我们也不过来
And nor do we ever talk about our private lives.
更不对外人讲我们的私生活
You... must come to us.
您  必须来我家
I'm Sorry, Mrs Johnson, my game, my turf, my rules.
抱歉  约翰逊夫人  我的地盘听我的
You'll have to talk over this with your husband
你得说服你丈夫
and then you can speak to me on the telephone.
然后给我打电话
Thank you very much for dropping by... Good afternoon.
感谢你来访  再见
And what if my husband were the Duke of York?
如果我丈夫是约克公爵呢
The Duke of York?
约克公爵
Yes... the Duke of York.
是的  约克公爵
I thought the appointment was for Johnson? Forgive me, your ...?
我以为预约的是约翰逊  抱歉  殿...
Royal Highness.
殿下
Johnson was used during the Great War;
大战时他用这个姓
when the Navy didn't want the enemy to know he was aboard.
皇家海军不想让敌人知道他在船上
Am I...considered the enemy?
我被当成敌人吗
You will be, if you remain unobliging.
是的  如果您不合作
And you have to have abosolute descretion.
而且你得严格保密
Of course. How did you find me, Your Royal Highness?
当然  殿下  您是怎么找到我的
The President of society of the Speech Therapists.
通过语言矫治协会的会长
Eileen McCleod? She's a sport.
艾琳·麦克卢尔  她是我的朋友
Dr McCleod warned me your
麦克卢尔医生提醒我说
antipodean methods were unorthodox and controversial.
您的澳洲式疗法是异端而且颇有争议
I warned her... those were not my favorite words.
我告诉她  我不爱听那些词
I can cure your husband.
我可以为您丈夫治疗
But for my method to work I need trust and total equality;
但用我的办法需要信任和彻底的平等
Here, in the safety of my consultation room.
并在我的诊室里进行
No exceptions.
概不例外
Well then, in that case...
那么  既然这样
When can you start?
您什么时候可以开始
Still sounds a bit rough, mate.
听起来还是有点刺耳  小伙子
You make me drive too slowly, Dad!
是你让我开得太慢了  老爸
Did you pick mum up from bridge?
你去桥那边接你妈了吗
Yes, I've hardly been out of the car all day.
是的  一整天我都开着车到处跑
I had a special visitor this afternoon.
今天下午  来了位特别的客人
- May I please leave this table.  - How special, special?
- 我可以离桌了吧  - 怎么个特别法
No, You must stay, bored stupid,
不行  小蠢蛋
listening to your parents'inane conversation.
你得留下来听你爸妈无聊的谈话
- Thanks Dad..  - and Mum.
- 谢谢爸爸  - 还有你妈
And mom.
谢谢妈妈
- Me too.  - You meeting Jean?
- 我也走了  - 去见简吗
No, someone else.
不是  别人
Doctor? Doctor? Can't you help your brother with the washing...
博士  博士  你能帮兄弟们洗碗吗
I'm fine.
我正忙着呢
Who's it Lionel?
是谁  莱昂内尔
Why bring it up if you can't talk about it?
不能说提它干嘛
Myrtle, It's just a woman, looking to help her husband.
莫特尔  只是一个女人  想帮她丈夫
Oh! And I had a call.
还有  我接到一个电话
For an audition.
得到一个试镜机会
- One of my favorites.  - Aren't they all?
- 我的最爱之一  - 所有角色不都是你最爱吗
It could be a lot of fun.
很有意思的角色
I'm sure you'll be splendid.
我相信你会做得很好
They're a highly regarded group.
是个有威望的剧团
From Putney.
来自普特尼
Tomorrow, Chapter IV.
明天读第四章
The flight
飞行
- Mama, I don't know they fly at all. - I can't wait
- 我都不知道他会飞  - 我都等不及了
Oh, to fly away
飞走了
Weren't they lucky!
他们不是很幸运吗
Now Papa tell a story!
那爸爸讲个故事吧
Could I be a penguin instead?
我装企鹅还不行吗
Well, now I want a penguin story.
我想听企鹅的故事
Very quickly.
讲个短的
Once, there were two princesses.
从前  有两个公主
Princess Elizabeth and Princess Margaret.
伊丽莎白公主和玛格丽特公主
whose Papa was a penguin.
她们的爸爸是只企鹅
This was because he had been turned into one by the wicket witch.
因为邪恶的女巫对他施了魔咒
This was an inconvenient for him.
这让他为难
Because he loved to hold his princesses in his arms...
因为他喜欢用手怀抱两个公主
and penguin can't because he has wings like herrings.
但企鹅不行  因为他长着青鱼般的翅膀
Herrings don't have wings.
青鱼没有翅膀
Penguins have wings which is shaped like herrings...
企鹅翅膀的形状像青鱼
and make matters worse...
但更糟的是
is that she sent him to the South Pole.
女巫把他扔到了南极
which is an awfully long walk back.
回来的路很遥远
if you can't fly.
除非会飞
So... When he reached the water,
所以  他来到水边
he dived in through the dept so fast...
迅速潜入水中
that he was in Southampton waters by lunchtime.
中午时他已抵达南汉普顿海域
And from there, he took the 2:30 to Weybridge,
在那儿搭两点半的船
changed at Clapham Junction and...
然后在克拉珀姆换船
asked a passing mallard the way to Buckingham Palace.
向一只路过的野鸭打听去白金汉宫的路
He swam up the Thames, out through the plughole,
他游过泰晤士河  从出水孔里钻出来
and gave the cook,
让厨师
Mama and Mrs Whittaker quite a shock.
妈妈还有惠特克太太吃了一惊
Now when the girls heard all the commotions,
女孩儿们听到了一片混乱
they ran to the kitchen where they gave him a good scrub,
她们跑进厨房给他彻底地洗了个澡
a mackerel and a kiss.
并给了他一条马鲛鱼和一个吻
and as they kissed him,
当她们吻他时
guess what he turned into?
猜他变成了什么
A handsome prince.
一个英俊的王子
A short- tailed Albatross.
一只短尾巴的信天翁
With wings so big...
有一双大翅膀
that he could wrap them both his two girls together.
这样他就可以一把搂过他的两个女儿了
Now, now... It's time for bed. Come on.
好了  该睡觉了  快点
Take these horses to stable.
把这两匹小马拉回马厩
- Quickly now, you have exactly a minute. - Good night.
- 动作快  就给你们1分钟  - 晚安
Feed them, bath them and to bed.
喂食  刷洗然后睡觉
Will Mrs Simpson be there?
辛普森夫人会参加吗
My brother's insisting.
我哥哥坚持让她来
Is he serious?
他是认真的吗
About her coming to dinner?
让她参加晚宴吗
No, about her.
不是  对她
A married woman? He can't be.
一个有夫之妇  他不会的
She can.
她会
By the way, I think I found someone rather interesting.
对了 我发现一个很有趣的人
On Harley Street. A doctor.
在哈里大街  一个医生
Out of the question.
绝不
I'm not having this conversation again. The matter's settled.
我不想再谈了  到此为止
His approach seems rather different....
他的方法好像很特别
Now?
现在开始吗
Now.
开始
"Now is the winter of our discontent,
如今约克之子把我们讨厌的冬天
Made glorious summer by this sun of York.
变成了灿烂的夏天
And all the clouds that lour'd upon our house
所有掠过我们家园的乌云
In the deep bosom of the ocean buried.
都被深埋在海洋的怀抱中
Now are our brows, bound with victorious... wreaths."
现在  我们的双眉周围缠绕着凯旋的花环
Thank you!
谢谢
Lovely diction Mr...?
发音不错  那谁
Logue. Lionel Logue.
罗格  莱昂内尔·罗格
Well, Mr.Logue.
罗格先生
I'm not hearing the cries
我听不出这是一个丑陋的家伙
of a deformed creature yearning to be King.
想要成为国王的呐喊
Nor did I realize Richard III was King of the Colonies.
也看不出理查三世像殖民地的国王
I do know all the lines. I've played the role before.
我知道所有台词  我演过这角色
- Sydney?  - Perth.
- 在悉尼吗  - 珀斯
Major theater town, is it?
剧场很多的城镇  对吧
Enthusiastic.
很狂热
I was well reviewed.
我经过了层层筛选
Yes... well, Lionel,
莱昂内尔
I think our dramatic society,
我们的戏剧社
is looking for someone slightly younger and a...
想找个年轻点的
little more regal.
更有帝王气质的人
You have to shut that one first. Put that one forth.
得先关上外面那个  再把这个往前推
Excellent.
很好
Where did you find this... physician?
你在哪找到的这个医生
Classifieds,
分类广告
next to 'French model, Shepherd's Market'.
紧挨着"法国模特  请联系牧羊菜市场"那条
He comes highly recommended.
有人强烈推荐他
Charges substantial fees in order to help the poor.
为了救济穷人他收取高昂的费用
Oh dear, perhaps he's a Bolshevik?!
天啊  或许他是共产主义者
Ah, there's no receptionist. Likes to keep things simple.
没有前台  他喜欢简单
Uh... The Johnsons.
我们是约翰逊夫妇
You can go in now, Mr. Johnson.
你可以进去了  约翰逊先生
Lionel says...
莱昂内尔说
wait here if you wish, Mrs Johnson.
如果你愿意可以在这等  约翰逊夫人
Or, it being a...
或者
pleasant day...
天气不错
perhaps take a stroll.
也许您可以去散步
Was that alright... Lionel?
我说的对吗  莱昂内尔
Marvellous! Willy.
棒极了  维利
You can stay and wait for your mom.
在这等妈妈来接你吧
Mrs Johnson...
约翰逊夫人
Mr Johnson, Do you come in?
约翰逊先生  您请进
Would you like a sweetie?
你喜欢糖果吗?
He's a good lad, Willy.
维利是个好孩子
He could hardly make a sound, you know,
第一次来见我时
when he first came to me.
他几乎一个音都发不出
My boys made those. They're good, aren't they?
我儿子们的杰作  不错吧
Please make yourself comfortable.
请随意
I was told not to sit too close.
有人告诉我不要坐得太近
Well I believe when speaking with a prince,
我认为和王子说话时
One waits for the prince to choose a topic.
要等王子选话题
Waiting for me to... commence
让我开始谈话
a conversation, one can wait a rather long wait.
那得等很久
Ah, yes, well...
呵  这样
Do you know any jokes?
您知道什么笑话吗
Timing isn't my strong suit.
计时不是我的强项
Cup of tea?
喝茶吗
No thank you.
不  谢谢
I think I'll have one.
我要来一杯
Aren't you going to start treating me, Dr Logue?
罗格医生您还不开始治疗吗
Only if you're interested in being treated.
除非您愿意被治疗
Please, call me Lionel.
请叫我莱昂内尔
I prefer Doctor.
我更愿称你为先生
I prefer Lionel.
我更愿被称为莱昂内尔
- What will I call you? - Your Royal Highness.
- 我该怎么称呼您  - 殿下
Then... it's "sir" after that.
之后可以称阁下
A little bit formal for here. I prefer names.
在这个场合太正式了  您的名字是
Prince Albert Frederick Arthur George.
阿尔伯特·弗雷德里克·亚瑟·乔治王子
How about Bertie?
叫博迪怎样
- Only my family uses that. - Perfect.
- 只有我的家人那么叫  - 很好
In here, it's better if we're equals.
在这里  我们平等相处比较好
If... if we were equals, I wouldn't be here.
如果我们真平等  我就不用来了
I'd be... at home with my wife
在家陪妻子
and no one would give a damn.
谁管我结不结巴
Please, Don't do that.
请不要抽烟
I'm sorry?
不要什么
I believe, sucking smoke into your lungs will kill you.
我认为抽烟对您的健康不利
My physicians say it relaxes the... the throat.
我的医生说这能放松喉...  喉咙
- They're idiots. - They've all been knighted.
- 一群白痴  - 他们都是御医
Makes it official then.
那就是官方认证的白痴
My castle, my rules.
我的地盘我做主
Thank you.
谢谢
What was your earliest memory?
请问你最早的记忆是
What on earth do you mean?
什  什么意思
Your first recollection.
你记得的第一件事
I'm not...
我不
here to discuss my personal matters.
不是来谈私事的
Why're you here then?
那您来干什么
Because I am bloody well stammer!
因为我他妈的结巴
You have a bit of a temper?
您还有点脾气
One of my many faults.
诸多缺点中的一个
When did the defect start?
结巴是从何时开始的
I've always been this way!
一直都这样
I doubt that.
我觉得不是
Don't tell me! It's my stammer!
你知道什么  结巴的是我
It's my field. I can assure you,
可我是专家  我向您保证
no infant starts to speak with a stammer.
口吃绝非天生
When did yours start?
您是几岁开始的
Four or five.
四五岁
That's typical.
一般都是这个年纪
So I've been told.
都这么说
I can't remember not doing it.
我记事起就结巴了
I can believe that.
我知道
Do you hesitate when you think?
您思考的时候也会停顿吗
Don't be ridiculous.
胡说
How about when you talk to yourself?
自言自语时呢
Everyone natters to themselves occasionally, Bertie.
博迪  所有人都会偶尔自言自语
Stop... stop calling me that.
别那么叫我
I'm not going to call you anything else.
我就这么叫
Then we shan't speak!
那就没什么好说了
Are you charging for this, Doctor?
医生  你收钱吗
A fortune.
收一大笔呢
I'll just let that brew.
泡一会再喝
So... when you talk to yourself, do you stammer?
那么  自言自语时  你结巴吗
No... of course not!
不结巴  当然不会
Well, that proves your impediment isn't a permanent part of you.
那证明您的口吃不是天生的
What do you think was the cause?
你觉得病因是什么
I don't... don't know.
我不 不知道
I... I don't... I don't care!
我...  我也不...  不在乎
I... I stammer!
我就是结巴
And no one can fix it.
没人能治好
I bet you, you can read flawlessly, right here, right now.
我打赌  您此时此刻就能流利地朗诵
And if I win the bet, I get to ask you more questions.
要是我赢  我就要问您更多问题
- And if I win? - You don't have to answer.
- 如果我赢呢  - 您不必回答
One usually... wagers money.
一般人都  都赌钱
A bob each to keep it sweet?
每人一先令作为开始
- Let's see your shilling. - I don't... carry money.
- 你出一先令  - 我不  不带钱
I had a funny feeling you mightn't.
就知道您没有
I'll stake you. And you can pay me back next time.
我借您  下回还我
Who says there is a next time?
谁说有下回
I haven't agreed to take you on, yet.
那倒是  我还没决定给您治疗
Please stand. And take a look at that.
请起立  看看这个
I can't... I can't read this.
我读  读不了
Well, then you owe me a shilling, for not trying.
您都没试就输给我一先令
To be... or not to be, that...
活着  还是死去  这...
I can't read!
我读不了
I haven't finished yet.
还没完呢
I'm going to record your voice
我用这机器给您录音
and then play it back to you on the same machine.
再放出来给您听
This is brilliant.
这机器棒极了
It's the latest thing from America. It's a Silvertone.
美国的最新产品  银音牌
Pop this on?
戴上这个
There's a bob in this, mate. You can go home rich!
伙计  这能赚一先令  您可以满载而归
- You're playing music. - I know.
- 这在放音乐  - 我知道
So how can I hear what I'm saying?
那我怎么听见自己说什么
Surely a Prince's brain knows what its mouth is doing.
王子的脑子肯定知道嘴在说什么
You're not well acquainted with Royal Princes, are you?
你一定不了解王子
Hopeless. Hopeless!
完全没用
You were sublime.
您读得非常好
Would I lie to a prince of the realm to win twelve pence?
我怎么会为了一先令欺骗王子殿下
I've no idea... what an Australian might do
我怎么知道一个澳洲人
for that sort of money.
为了那点钱会做出什么
Let me play it back to you.
我放出来给您听听
No.
不用
All right then, I get to ask you the question.
那好吧  我就要提问了
Thank you, Doctor,
谢谢你  医生
I don't feel... this is for me.
我觉得这治不好我
Thank You for your time, Bye.
麻烦你了  再见
Sir?
阁下
The recording is free.
录音是免费的
Please keep it as a souvenir.
请收下做纪念
No.
没用
乔治五世
1934年圣诞讲话
诺福克郡  桑德林姆宫
For the present,
当前形势下
the work to which we are all equally bound,
我们共同担当的重任
is to arrive at a reasoned tranquillity
便是在全国之内
within our borders,
营造和平平静的环境
to regain prosperity at this time of depression,
在此萧条期间
without self- seeking...
摒弃私心
and to carry with us those whom the burden of past years...
与我们这些为之前的重负倍感灰心与挫折的人
has disheartened or overborne.
再图繁荣
To all, to each, I wish a Happy Christmas.
祝每位国民圣诞快乐
God bless you.
上帝保佑你们
And off air.
直播结束
Easy when you know how.
熟能生巧
Sir.
阁下
Have a go yourself.
你来试试
- Congratulations, Sir. - Mr. Wood.
- 演讲很成功  陛下  - 伍德先生
Splendid fellow.
他很厉害
Chap taught me everything I know.
教会我最重要的一条
Let the microphone do the work.
麦克风自然会播音
- Sir. - Thank you.
- 阁下  - 谢谢
Gentlemen.
各位这边走
Sit up, straight back,
挺胸坐直
face boldly up to the bloody thing and stare it square in the eye,
抬头面对话筒  直视它
as you would any decent Englishman.
当它是个平民
Show who's in command.
拿出皇家气派
Papa, I don't think I can read this.
爸爸  我觉得我读不了
This devilish device will change everything if you don't.
如果读不了  这该死的东西能毁了一切
In the past all a King had to do was
过去一个国王要做的事情
look respectable in uniform and not fall off his horse.
就是穿上正装摆摆样子  别掉下马
Now, we must invade people's homes...
现在我们必须进入平常百姓家
and ingratiate ourselves with them.
去讨好他们
This family's been reduced
所谓皇室家族
to those lowest, basest of all creatures.
已经降为最低等的平民
We've become actors!
我们变成了演员
We're not a family, we're a firm.
我们不是皇室  而是公司
Yet at any moment, some of us may be out of work.
然而某些成员随时会失业
Your darling brother, and future king!
你的兄长  我的王储
The only wife he appears interested in
他唯一感兴趣的妻子
is invariably the wife of another!
无一例外都是有夫之妇
He's broken off with Lady Furness.
他和弗勒斯女士分手了
And taken up a Mrs. Simpson,
又看上了辛普森夫人
a woman with two husbands living!
一个已经结过两次婚的女人
I told him straight,
我跟他直说
no divorced person could ever be received at court.
皇室不会接受这种女人
He said it made him sublimely happy.
他说他感到十分幸福
I imagined that was because she was sleeping with him.
我想这是因为她已经和他上床了
"I give you my word," this is what he said.
他说  "我保证"
"I give you my word we've never had immoral relations."
"我们绝没发生不正当关系"
stared square into his father's face and lied!
当着他父亲的面撒谎
When I'm dead, that boy will ruin himself,
等我死了  他用不了一年
this family and this nation within twelve months.
就会毁掉自己  毁掉这个家族  毁掉这个国家
Who'll pick up the pieces, hmm?
到时谁收拾残局
Herr Hitler intimidating half of Europe.
希特勒震慑了半个欧洲
Marshall Stalin the other half.
另半个在马歇尔·斯大林掌控
Who'll stand between us,
谁来保护英国
the jackboots, and the proletarian abyss?
免遭纳粹军队和无产阶级的侵犯
You?
你能行吗
Well,
这样的话
with your older brother shirking his duties,
你哥哥逃避责任
you're going to have to do a lot more of this.
你势必将更多地做这事情
Have a go yourself.
你自己来一次
- With the wireless... - Get it out, boy!
- 通过无线电  - 别紧张  孩子
- one of the... marvels of... - Modern.
- 这一伟大的  现  - 现代
Just take your time, form your words carefully.
慢慢来  小心组词
- science, I am enabled... - Relax!
- 现代科技  我能够  - 放松
- Just try it! - This Chrismas Day...
- 大胆说  - 在这个圣诞节
to speak to all my...
向我的...
Do it!
说啊
Lying .. bastard.
骗人的混蛋
- "You're playing music. - I know.
- 这在放音乐  - 我知道
So how can I hear what I'm saying?
我怎么知道自己说什么
Surely a Prince's brain knows what its mouth is doing?
王子的大脑肯定知道嘴在说什么
You're not well acquainted with Royal Princes, are you?
你不了解王子
To be, or not to be, that is the question.
活着  还是死去  这是个难题
whether tis nobler in the mind to suffer...
哪一种选择更为高贵
the slings and arrows of outrageous fortune,
是甘心忍受残暴命运的飞箭流石
or to take arms against a sea of troubles,
还是奋起搏击无边的苦海
and by opposing end them?
通过反抗一了百了
To die, to sleep no more,
死去  睡去  仅此而已
and by a sleep to say we end...
如果说睡去能了结
is the heartache and the thousand natural shocks...
肉体注定要承受的伤心
that flesh is heir to. Tis a consummation...
以及千百次的打击  那可是...
Hopeless. Hopeless!"
完全没用
Strictly business.
只能治病
No... personal nonsense.
别  打听私事
I thought I'd made that very clear in our interview.
我想在之前的会面我已经说清楚了
Have you got the shilling you owe me?
欠我那一先令带了吗
No, I haven't.
没带
Didn't think so.
没想到
Besides, you tricked me!
而且上次你耍花招了
Physical excercises and tricks are important...
身体操练和花招很重要
What you're asking
你们的要求
will only deal with the surface of the problem.
只能治标不治本
Is that effecient?
那不是更有效吗
No, as far as I see it,
在我看来
my husband has mechanical difficulties with his speech.
我丈夫只是在演讲时有身体上的困难
Maybe just deal with that.
也许处理这个就可以了
I'm willing to work hard, Doctor Logue.
我愿意刻苦练习  罗格医生
Lionel.
叫我莱昂内尔
Are you... are you willing to do your part?
你愿意治我吗
Alright. You want mechanics?
行  你想治身体对吧
We need to relax your jaw muscles
我要放松你的颚肌
and strengthen your tongue by repeating tongue twisters
练习绕口令  锻炼舌头
For example, "I'm a thistle- sifter.
比如说  四是四  十是十
I have a sieve of sifted thistles and...
十四是十四
a sieve of unsifted thistles because I am a thistle- sifter.
四十是四十
Fine!
行
You do have a flabby tummys,
你的腹肌比较松软
we need spend some times to strength in your diaphragm.
我们要花时间增强你的横膈膜力量
Simple mechanics.
很简单的物理治疗
That is all we ask.
我们就需要这个
And that's about a shilling's worth.
那我只收一先令就够了
Forget about the bloody shilling!
别提他妈的先令
Perhaps, upon occasions...
我可能时不时地
you might be requested to assist...
需要你帮  帮忙
in coping with... some minor event.
应付些活动
Will that be agreeable?
你同意吗
Of course.
当然
Yes. And that will be the full extent of your services.
好  您的任务就这些
Shall I see you next week?
那下周见
I shall see you every day.
我们要天天见
Feel the loosening of the jaw.
感觉下巴放松
Good. Little bounces, bounces. Shoulders loose.
好  来蹦两下  蹦  放松肩膀
Now lips.
来  甩嘴唇
Take a nice deep breath. Expand your chest..
深吸一口气  扩张胸腔
put your hands on your ribs.
把手放在肋骨上
Deeper, good.
继续吸  好
How do you feel?
感觉如何
Full of hot air.
满腹废话
Isn't that what public speaking is all about?
演说不就是这样吗
My wife and I are glad to visit this important...
我妻子和我很荣幸来参观如此重要的
Take a good deep breath, and up comes Her Royal Highness
深深吸气  把殿下顶起来
and slowly exhale, and down comes Her Royal Highness.
慢慢呼气  把殿下放下
- You alright, Bertie? - Yes.
- 博迪你还好吗  - 好
This is actually quite good fun.
这还挺好玩
- Mmm... mother.
母... 母亲
- Shorter time each time. - Mmm...mother.
- 每次都加快  - 母亲
- Mmm... manufactoring district. - Another deep breathe...
- 模...  模范工业产区  - 再吸气
- Jack and Jill... - Jack and Jill...
- 吃葡萄  - 吃葡萄
- went up the hill. - went up the hill.
- 不吐葡萄皮  - 不吐葡萄皮
Now just sway.
现在前后摆动
Perfect.
很好
We'll not permit us to...
我们不  不愿
- Loosen the shoulders. - Ding dong bell,
- 放松肩膀  - 打南边来了个喇嘛
which is in the well... who put any little ton in ten...
手里提着五斤鳎?  打北边来了个哑巴
Still short memory, Bertie, come on.
还不长记性  博迪  继续
- A cow. - A cow.
- 一头牛  - 一头牛
- A king. - A king.
- 一个国王  - 一个国王
Anyone who can shout vows in a open window
只要能站在窗前掉嗓
can learn to deliver a speech.
就能学会演讲
Fourty... fifty!
40秒  50秒
- Take a deep breath, and... - It is...
- 深深吸气  - 今天
- Let the words flow. - Knight as a bloody wack...
- 然后脱口而出  - 狗屁御医都他妈没用
Come on. One more time, Bertie, do it!
再来一次博迪  加油
a sieve of sifted thistles...
十四是十四
- Father. Father. - F... father. Father.
- 父亲  父亲  - 父...  父亲  父亲
- Name of the "th", father. - Father. F... father. Father.
- 唇齿音  父  - 父亲  父亲  父亲
桑德林姆宫
1936年
- Hello, Bertie. - Hello David.
- 博迪  - 大卫
- How did you come out. - Not at all.
- 你怎么站在外面  - 没事
You waiting long?
等很久了吗
Christ, it's bloody freezing.
老天  真他妈冷
Where've you been?
去哪了
- I've Been busy. - So was I.
- 到处忙  - 我也是
Elizabeth has pneumonia.
伊丽莎白得了肺炎
I'm sorry. She'll recover.
真可怜  她会康复的
Father won't.
父亲就难说了
I'll drive.
我开车
Old bugger's doing this on purpose.
老家伙这是成心的
Dying?
成心要死吗
Departing prematurely...
提前离席
to complicate matters with Wallis.
恶化和威利斯(辛普森夫人)的关系
For heaven's sake, David. You know how long he's been ill.
得了吧  大卫  他都病这么久了
Wallis explained.
威利斯是这么想的
She's terribly clever about these things.
她对这种事很明白
Whereas by letters patent under the Great Seal,
1912年6月11日于威斯敏斯特
bearing date of Westminster, the eleventh June, 1912
上诏加盖国玺
His Majesty King George the Fifth did constitute...
乔治五世陛下宣布
- order and declare that there should be a guardian, - What's going on here.
- 任命国家议会  - 怎么了
- Custos Regni... - I cannot follow you. I'm confused that and...
- 监国  - 我  我没明白  不理解
- in the form of council of state. - I don't understand what you are talking about...
- 代天巡守  - 我不懂你在说什么
It's the order of the Council for the State, Sir.
阁下  这是有关英国议会的决议
So we may act on your behalf...
授权我们代您行政
talk clearer to me, I'm afraid...
说  说清楚点  我
- I'm so confused but... - Approved.
- 我一点都不明白  - 通过
Thank you.
谢谢
Give me your hand, sir.
阁下  请伸手
Thank you.
谢谢
Feeling a little better, Sir?
感觉好点吗  阁下
No. I'm not feeling any better. I feel dreadful.
没有  不好  太难受了
Been, Uh, ice skating? Ice skating?
你滑冰  滑冰去了吗
No, no, George.
没有  乔治
Yes, yes, he's alright, of course.
是  是  他好着呢
I know, darling, a talk, even a lovely long talk,
亲爱的我知道  即使聊再长时间
is a poor substitute for holding tight and making drowsy.
也比不上紧密的拥抱和小酌微醺
Nor making our own drowsies either,
我们也不能小醉了
as we've had to do far too often lately.
因为最近酒会太多
David, dinner?
大卫  来吃晚饭
I'm on with Wallis!
我跟威利斯说话呢
Bertie. No. No, it's not important.
是博迪  不  不  这无所谓
I don't want to! No!
我不想当国王  真的
I'll phone you later.
晚点打给你
Bye, bye.
再见
Wallis misses me terribly.
威利斯很想我
Mama says you're late for dinner.
妈妈说你晚饭迟到了
She forgets
她忘了
Papa's bloody clocks were always half an hour fast.
爸爸的钟都快半小时
How is the King? I hope he is not in pain.
陛下怎样  他没在痛吧
No, no, sir. His Majesty is quieter now.
没有  阁下  陛下现在平静多了
Thank you.
谢谢
David, if your father were here,
大卫  你父王要在场
tardiness would not be tolerated.
不会容忍你迟到
None of this unpleasantness would be tolerated.
也不会容忍这样不愉快的事情发生
You know sir, I appreciate that
殿下  如您所知  我很欣赏您
you are different from your father
您与令尊相比
both in outlook and temperament.
目光远大  性格温和
I want you to know that...
我想告诉您
whenever the King questioned your conduct,
只要国王质疑您的行为
I tried in your interest,
我都是站在您的立场上
to present it in a most favourable light.
为您的利益着想
I can always trust you to have my best interests at heart.
我相信您心里时刻想着'国王'的利益
I fear, our vigil will not be of long duration.
恐怕国王大限将至
Please continue.
各位请慢用
We commend our brother George...
我们将乔治弟兄
to the mercy of God, our Maker and Redeemer.
交予仁慈的天父  我们的造物主和救赎者
Long live the King.
国王万岁
I hope, I will make good as he has made good.
我希望  我能做得和他一样好
What on earth was that?
这到底是谁怎么了
Poor Wallis. Now I'm trapped!
可怜的威利斯  这下我陷入困境了
Time for a Shake, dad?
来段莎士比亚的戏吧  爸爸
You sure?
真的要吗
Go on.
来吧
Put your thinking caps on.
准备好猜谜
Bet its the Scottish Play.
我猜是《麦克白》
No, I bet it's Othello. It's always Othello.
不对  肯定《奥赛罗》  总是《奥赛罗》
Are thou afeard.
害怕吗
Be not afeard.
不要怕
Caliban!
凯列班[莎士比亚剧《暴风雨》中角色]
Oh! For heaven's sake... that was a lucky guess!
老天  肯定是蒙对的
Don't listen to egghead. Go on, Dad.
别听那书呆子的  继续  爸爸
The isle is full of noises, sounds and sweet airs,
岛上回响着各种声音  空气宜人
that give delight, and hurt not.
讨人喜欢  没有伤害
Sometimes a thousand twanging instruments...
有时无数叮咚乐器声
will hum about mine ears,
在我耳边鸣响
and sometimes voices, that, if then...
有时我酣睡醒来
I had waked after long sleep will make me sleep again.
听见歌声  又使我沉沉睡去
Alright, clever clogs, what comes next?
好了  小机灵鬼  下一句是什么
And then, in dreaming, the clouds methought would open,
于是在梦里  我以为云要散了
and show riches ready to drop upon me...
昭示财富将临  醒来之后
that when I'm awaked, I cried to dream again.
醒来之后  我含泪重又入梦
It's such a sad thought.
这可真悲痛
My next patient must be early.
肯定是我的下一个病人来早了
You better go lads, I'm sorry.
你们得走了  小伙子们  对不起
Won't be a moment, Clifford.
马上来  克利福德
Bertie!
博迪
They told me not to expect you.
他们告诉我说你不来了
I am sorry about your father.
节哀顺变
I don't wish to intrude.
希望没有打扰您
Oh no... Please come in.
没有没有  请进
I've been practising. One hour a day. In spite of everything.
我一直在练习  无论如何每天练一小时
What's going on there?
你那儿怎么了
I was, sorry, mucking around with my kids.
不好意思  我在跟孩子们胡闹
Do you feel like working today?
你今天想进行练习吗
A Curtis bi- plane.
柯蒂斯双翼飞机
I'll put on some hot milk.
我来准备点热牛奶
Logue, I'd kill for something stronger.
罗格  我喝点刺激的
I wasn't there for my father's death.
我父亲临终前我不在
Still makes me sad.
这让我抱憾至今
I can imagine so.
我可以想像
What did you father do?
你父亲是干什么的
He was a brewer.
他是个酿酒的
At least there was free beer.
至少喝酒不要钱
Here's to the memory of your father.
这杯来缅怀您父亲
I was informed, after the fact...
后来  他们告诉我
that my father's last words were,
我父亲的临终遗言是
Bertie has more guts than the rest of his brothers put together.
博迪比其他几个兄弟加一起更勇敢
He couldn't say that to my face.
他没能直接对我说
My brother.
我哥哥
What about him?
他怎么了
Try singing it.
试着唱出来
I'm sorry.
什么
What songs do you know?
你会唱什么歌
Songs?
唱歌
Yes, songs.
对  唱歌
"Swanee River"?
《史瓦尼河》
I love that song.
我喜欢那首歌
Happens to be my favorite.
刚好也是我的最爱
Sing me the chorus.
给我唱唱副歌部分
No. Certainly not.
不  当然不行
Always wanted to build models.
我以前总想做模型
Father... father wouldn't allow it.
父亲不让
He collected stamps. So we had to collect stamps.
他集邮  所以我们都得跟着集邮
You can finish that off. If you sing.
如果您唱歌  就可以把这个做完
My brother David. Dum, dum, dum- dum...
我哥哥大卫  笨  笨  笨瓜
I'm not going to sit here, wobbling.
我可不想在这瞎哼哼
You can with me.
你可以跟着我唱
Because you're peculiar.
因为你是个怪人
I take that as a compliment.
我就当你在夸我
Rules are rules.
按规矩来
I'm not crooning "Swanee River".
我才不哼《史瓦尼河》
"Camptown Races" then.
那唱《康城赛马》
My brother David, he said to me, doo- dah
我哥哥大卫告诉我  嘟哒
doo- dah... Continuous sound will give you flow.
嘟哒  持续发音可以让您说话流利
Does it feel strange, now that David's on the throne?
现在大卫当国王了  会不会感觉很奇怪
To tell the truth,
说实话
it was a relief...
这是种解脱
knowing I wouldn't be... King.
知道自己当不了国王
But unless he produces an heir, you're next in line.
可除非他有孩子  否则您就是下一任
And your daughter, Elizabeth, would then succeed you.
然后是您的女儿伊丽莎白继任
You're barking up the wrong tree now, Doctor, Doctor.
医生啊医生  你是在胡说
Lionel See? You didn'stammer.
叫我莱昂内尔  看  你不结巴了
Of course I didn't stammer, I was singing!
我当然不结巴  我在唱歌
Well, as a little reward,
作为奖励
you get to put some glue on these struts.
您可以在支架上抹点胶水
Your boy, won't mind?
你儿子不会介意吧
No, not at all.
不  完全不会
David and I were very close.
大卫和我曾经很亲密
Young bucks... You know.
你知道  年轻人嘛
Did you chase the same girls?
你们追一个姑娘
David was always very helpful in arranging introductions.
安排引见的时候大卫总是很帮得上忙
We shared the expert ministrations of Paulette in Paris.
我们都受到了巴黎的波莱特无微不至的照顾
Not at the same time of course.
当然不是同一个时候
Did David ever tease you?
大卫嘲笑过你吗
Yes, they all did. Buh- buh- buh- Bertie?
他们都嘲笑过  博- 博- 博- 博迪
Father encouraged it.
父亲纵容他们
Said,"Get it out, boy!" Said it would make me stop.
说"别紧张  孩子"  说这样能让我不结巴
Said that "I sas afraid of my father,
他说"我害怕我父亲
and my children are damn well going to be afraid of me."
我的孩子必须也得怕我"
Are you naturally right handed?
你天生就是右撇子吗
Left. I was... punished. Now I use the right.
左撇子  我被迫改过来的  现在我习惯右手了
Yes, that's very common with stammerers.
没错  这种情况在结巴中很常见
Anything other corrections?
还做过别的矫正吗
Knock knees.
X型腿
Metal splints were made. Worn... worn day and night.
整天都得戴着金属夹板
- That must have been painful. - Bloody agony.
- 那一定很疼  - 疼死了
Straight legs now.
现在腿直了
Who were you closest to in your family?
你同哪个家人最亲近
Nannies. Not my first nanny.
乳母们  不是第一个
She loved David... hated me.
她喜欢大卫  讨厌我
When we are presented to my...
我们被带去
parents for the daily viewing,
觐见父母的时候
she'd pinch me..
她会掐我
I'd cry and be handed back to her immediately.
我就哭  然后被立刻交回给她
And then she would...
然后  她就
Sing it.
唱出来
"Then she wouldn't feed me. Far far away."
"然后她就不喂我"
Took my parents... three years to notice.
三年之后我父母才发现
As you can imagine, it caused some stomach problems. Still.
胃会出毛病一点都不奇怪  直到现在
What about your brother, Johnny?
你弟弟约翰尼呢
Were you close to him?
你和他亲近吗
Johnny.
约翰尼
Sweet boy.
好孩子
Had...
得了...
epilepsy.
得了癫痫
And he was... different.
他不一样
He died at... 13.
13岁就去世了
hidden from view.
不曾在公开场合出现
I'm... I'm told it's not... catching.
他们告诉我这病不传染
Do you want a top- up?
再来一杯吗
Please.
谢谢
You know...
你知道吗
Lionel, you're...
莱昂内尔  你是...
you're the first ordinary Englishman...
你是英国平民中第一个...
Australian.
澳大利亚平民
I've ever really spoken to.
(英国平民中第一个)同我真正交谈的
When I'm... driven through the streets and see the,
当我坐在车里穿过街道时
you know, the common man staring at me,
看见那些平民注视着我
I'm struck by how little I know of his life,
我总为我对他的生活一无所知
and how little he knows of mine.
和他对我的生活一无所知而感到震惊
Thank you.
谢谢
What're friends for.
朋友就是倾诉对像
I wouldn't know.
我本来不会明白
苏格兰 巴尔莫勒尔堡
I sifted seven... thick- stalked thistles trough a strong, thick sieve.
我用一个结实的大筛子...  筛了七个粗茎蓟草
I sifted seven thick- stalked...
我筛了七个粗茎蓟草
That's enough now, darling.
可以了  亲爱的
I have to keep doing this, it's awful.
说的差劲  我得接着练
I sifted seven... thick- stalked... - Oh, no.
- 我筛了七个粗茎蓟草  - 不会吧
One hundred year old spruces... removed to improve the view!
百年的云杉  为了开阔视野就这么砍了
Who does she think she is!
她以为她是谁
Nonetheless... we must try to be pleasant towards Mrs Simpson.
不管怎样  我们必须对辛普森夫人尽量亲切友好一些
You know she calls me the Fat Scottish Cook?
你知道她管我叫"苏格兰胖厨子"吗
You're not fat.
你又不胖
I'm getting plump.
我快要发福了
You seldom cook.
你不下厨
I sifted seven... - Shut up!
- 我筛了七个...  - 闭嘴
trough a strong... thick sieves...
结实的大筛子...  粗茎蓟草
再次说反 囧||
I sifted seven...
我筛了七个...
Their Royal Highnesses the Duke and Duchess of York.
约克郡公爵与公爵夫人殿下驾到
How lovely to see you both.
见到你们俩真高兴
Welcome to our little country shack.
欢迎来到我们的乡间小屋
I came at the invitation of the King.
国王邀请我才来的
Your Majesty.
国王陛下
- You all right? - Sorry we're late.
- 路上顺利吗  - 抱歉我们来晚了
Very nice to see you.
很高兴见到你
Mrs. Simpson.
辛普森夫人
Very nice.
很高兴
Hello David.
大卫
Making some... changes to the garden, I see.
我发现你在...  改造花园
Yes, I am not quite finished yet.
对  还没弄完
Don't tell me I behaved badly, Mr Churchill.
别告诉我我表现不礼貌  丘吉尔先生
On the contrary, your Royal Highness. Etiquette decrees
恰恰相反  殿下  礼仪规定
royalty must be greeted by the official host,
皇室成员应当被正式主人接待
in this case, the King. Not a commoner.
在此  就应该是国王  而不是平民
Thank you.
谢谢
What is her hold on him?
她是怎么迷住他的
I have no idea.
不知道
Apparently she has certain skills...
显然她在上海国教教会
acquired in an establishment in Shanghai.
学会了某些技巧
David.
大卫
Just be a sec, darling. Would you excuse me?
马上  亲爱的  失陪一下
David, I've been trying to see you...
大卫  我一直想见你
I've been terribly busy.
我忙得焦头烂额
Doing what?
忙什么
- Kinging. - Really?
- 当国王  - 真的吗
Kinging... is a precarious business these days.
如今当国王如履薄冰
Where is the Russian Tsar? Where is Cousin Wilhelm?
俄罗斯的沙皇何在  德国的威廉皇帝何在
You're being dreary.
你可真没趣
Is Kinging laying off 80... staff
难道当国王要把桑德林汉姆夏宫80个臣属革职
and buying more pearls for Wallis
给威利斯买更多的珍珠
while people are marching across Europe singing the Red Flag?
而此时共产主义者已席卷了整个欧洲大陆
Stop your worrying. Herr Hitler will sort them out.
你别操心了  希特勒先生会解决这些问题
And who'll sort out Herr Hitler?
那谁来解决希特勒先生
Where's the bloody '23?
那瓶该死的二三年陈酿在哪
And you've put that woman into our mother's suite?
你甚至让那女人住进妈妈的套房
Mother's not still in the bed, is she?
妈妈不再睡床了  不是吗
That's not funny.
这不好笑
Here it is. Wallis likes the very best.
就是这个  威利斯只喜欢最好的
I don't care what woman you carry on with at night,
我不关心你晚上跟哪个女人暧昧
as long as you show up for duty in the morning!
只要你白天履行身为国王的职责
Wallis is not just some woman I am carrying on with.
威利斯不只是跟我暧昧
We intend to marry.
我们准备结婚了
Excuse me?
你说什么
She's filing a petition for divorce.
她正在申请离婚
Good God.
老天
Can't you just give her a nice house and a title?
你就不能给她间好房子  再给她封个爵位吗
I'm not having her as my mistress.
我不会让她做我的情妇的
The Church doesn't recognize divorce,
教会不允许离婚
and you are the... head of the Church.
而你正是...  教会的领袖
Haven't I any rights?
我难道一点权利也没有吗
Many privileges...
你有很多特权
Not the same thing.
不是一回事
Your beloved common man may marry for love,
平民都能为了爱情结婚
why not me?
我怎么就不行
If you were... a common man,
你要是...  一个平民
on what basis could you... possibly claim to be King?
又凭什么加冕为王
Sounds like you've studied our wretched Constitution.
听起来你对我们这悲惨的宪法很有研究
Sounds like you haven't.
听起来你没研究
That's what this is about.
这就是你的目的吗
Brushing up. Hence, the elocution lessons?
从演讲课开始  反覆练习
That's the scoop around town.
这可是镇上的奇闻
I'm trying to...
我是想
Yearning for a larger audience are we, B- B- B- B- Bertie?
想再多些听众吗  博  博  博  博  博迪
Don't...
别
What's that?
别什么
I'm sorry, I...
抱歉  我...
Younger brother trying to push older brother off the throne..
弟弟想把哥哥赶下王位
P- P- P- P- Positively medieval.
还  还  还  还  还真老套
Wallis.
威利斯
Ah. Where have you been all this time?
你上哪儿去了
- Who have you been talking to? - Never you mind.
- 你跟谁聊天呢  - 不要你管
What a very complicated little King you are.
你究竟是怎样一个让人难以揣摩的国王呢
I try to be.
你喜欢就好
All that work... down the drain.
所有的努力都付之东流
My own brother...
我亲生的哥哥
I couldn't say a single word to him in reply.
我居然对着他一个字都说不出来
Why do you stammer so much more with David than you ever do with me?
为什么你跟大卫说话比跟我说话结巴得多
Because you're bloody well paid to listen!
因为你收了一大笔钱听我说话
Bertie, I'm not a geisha girl.
博迪  我可不是陪聊的艺伎
Stop trying to be so bloody clever!
别说俏皮话了
What is it about David that stops you speaking?
大卫怎么会让你说不出话
What is it about you that bloody well makes...
你是怎么回事  他妈成天
you want to go on about him, the whole bloody time.
没完没了纠结这个问题
Vulgar but fluent. You don't stammer when you swear.
粗鄙  但很流利  你骂人的时候从不结巴
Bugger off!
滚蛋
Is that the best you can do?
你只会骂这个吗
Well, bloody bugger to you, you beastly bastard.
去你妈的  你这禽兽不如的混蛋
A public school prig can do better than that.
公共学校的道学先生都比你会骂人
Shit!
日
Shit, shit, shit.
日  日  日
Shit, shit, shit, shit, shit, shit, shit.
日  日  日  日  日  日  日
Shit! Shit! - Yes!
- 日  日  - 这就对了
See how defecation flows trippingly from the tongue?
看脏话从舌尖喷涌而出
Because I'm angry!
因为我怒了
You Know the f- word?
你会说那个F开头的词吗
Fornication?
通奸
Oh Bertie.
博迪  别装
Fuck.
操
Fuck, fuck, fuck, fucking fuck!
操  操  操  操它的操
Fuck, fuck and bugger!
操  操且兽性大发
Bugger, bugger, buggedy, buggedy.
鸡奸  兽奸
Buggedy, fuck, fuck, ass
鸡奸  操  操  菊花
- Yes! You see! Not a hesitation! - Balls, balls, fuckety shit, shit,
- 没错  你看  一点也不打磕  - 鸟  鸡巴  操日  日
Willy, shit and fuck! And tits.
日  混蛋  混蛋  操  操  奶头
Dad? What's going on?
爸
Sorry. Finish your homework
抱歉  做作业去
Well...That's a side of you we don't get to see that often.
我们很少见到你这一面
No. No we're not supposed to really, not publicly.
我们不该这样的  不能公开这样
Let's get some air.
出去透透气吧
No, Logue, I don't think that's a good idea.
不  罗格  我不认为这是个好主意
What's the matter? What's got you so upset?
怎么了  什么让你这么沮丧
Logue, you have no idea.
罗格  你都想不到
My brother is infatuated with a woman who's been married twice.
我哥哥迷恋一个结过两次婚的女人
She's asking for a divorce and David is determined to marry her.
她正在申请离婚  而大卫决定要娶她
Mrs. Wallis Simpson of Baltimore.
巴尔的摩的威利斯·辛普森夫人
That's not right. Queen Wallis of Baltimore?
不对  以后就是巴尔的摩的威利斯皇后
Unthinkable.
难以想像
Can he do that?
他能这么做吗
Absolutely not. But he's going to anyway.
当然不能  但他决意如此
All hell's broken loose.
所有事情全乱套了
Can't they carry on privately?
他们不能偷偷的继续吗
If only they would.
要是他们愿意就好了
Where does that leave you?
你的立场是什么
I know my place.
我知道我的本份
I'll do anything...
我会尽我一切所能
in my power to keep my brother on the throne.
让我哥哥继续留在王位上
Is it that serious?
你是认真的
Your place may well be on the throne.
也许做国王是你的本份
I am not an alternative to my brother.
我不是我哥哥的替代者
You can outshine David.
如果你是国王  你会做的比大卫更好
Don't take liberties!
别乱说
That's bordering on treason.
这近乎叛国
I'm just saying you could be King. You could do it!
我只是说你可以做国王  你能做到
That is treason!
这是叛国
I'm trying to get you to realise...
我只是想让你明白
- you need not be governed by fear. - I've had enough of this!
- 你不用被恐惧控制  - 够了
What're you so afraid of?
你到底在怕什么
Your poisonous words!
你这些讨厌的话
Why'd you come to me?
那你为什么来找我
You are not some middle class bugger,
你可不是什么中产阶级人士
who needs elocution lessons so you can chit- chat...
上了演讲课去跟别人胡扯
Don't instruct me on my duties!
别对我的事指手画脚
I'm the son of a.... King.
我是国王的儿子
The brother of a king.
国王的弟弟
You're the disappointing son of a brewer!
你只是酿酒师没出息的儿子
A jumped- up jackeroo from the outback!
一个澳洲乡下来的暴发户
You're nobody.
你什么都不是
These sessions are over!
疗程结束
花园入口
首相办公室
唐宁街十号
It's not because she's an American. That is the least of it.
不是因为她是美国人  那不算什么
It's because she is a soon to be a twice divorced American,
是因为她是一个就要离婚两次的美国人
And the King, as head of The Church of England...
而国王作为英国国教的最高领袖
can not marry a divorced woman.
不能娶一个离过婚的女人
And Sir, I apologize for the nature of this.
阁下  我对此感到遗憾
According to Scotland Yard,
根据苏格兰场的调查
the King has not always possess exclusive rights to Mrs. Simpson's favours and affections,
国王并不是辛普森夫人唯一的爱人
sharing them with a married used car salesman,
她另有一个情人  是个二手汽车商人
a certain Mr Guy Trundle.
名叫盖伊·特兰德尔
In addition, it is also rumoured...
而且  还有传言说
Hitler's ambassador, Count von Ribbentrop,
希特勒的大使  坎特·冯·李宾特洛普
sends her 17 carnations every day.
每天给她送十七支康乃馨
Should His Majesty continue to ignore the advice of His Government,
如果你哥哥继续无视内阁的忠告
he must abdicate.
他必须退位
Otherwise His Government has no choice but to resign.
否则内阁别无选择  只能辞职
Prime Minister,
首相
you'd leave the country without a... a government?
你要让这个国家没有内阁
Does the King do what he wants,
一个国王该做他想做的
or does he do what his people expect him to do?
还是该做他的人民想让他做的
What's the matter, love?
怎么了  亲爱的
I'm Just having trouble with a patient.
我只是为一个病人苦恼
That isn't like you.. Why?
这可不像你  为什么苦恼
He's scared...
他很害怕
H's afraid of his own shadow.
害怕他自己的影子
Isn't that why they come to you?
他们不就是为了这个来找你吗
This fellow could be really somebody great,
这个人真的可以很优秀
and he's fighting me.
但他反对我的说法
Perhaps, he doesn't want to be great.
可能他不想成为优秀的人
Perhaps that's what you want.
也许是你一厢情愿
I might have overstepped the mark.
我可能有点过分了
Apologize,
去道歉
do you both good.
对你们俩都好
I'm very sorry, Mr Logue, the Duke is busy.
很抱歉  罗格先生  公爵大人很忙
I'm happy to wait. Or I could come back later.
我可以等  或者晚点再来
As I said, the Duke is terribly busy.
我说了  公爵大人非常忙
Thank you.
谢谢
The parliament will not support their marriage.
议会不会支持这桩婚姻的
But there were other reasons for concern.
但还有其他顾虑  阁下
He was careless with state papers.
他不关心国家政策
He lacked commitment and resolve.
他不承担义务  缺少决心
There were those that worried
还有人担心
where he would stand when war comes with Germany .
如果同德国开战  他是什么立场
We're not coming to that?
我们不会走到那一步吧
Indeed we are, Sir.
绝对会  阁下
Prime Minister Baldwin may deny this,
鲍德温首相也许会否认这点
but Hitler's intent is crystal clear.
但希特勒的野心昭然若揭
War with Germany will come,
与德国大战在即
and we will need a King behind whom we can all stand behind, united.
而我们需要一个带领我们团结一致的国王
I fear my... brother is not of...
我担心  此时我哥哥
sound mind, at this time.
还没有看清形势
Have you thought what you will call yourself?
你想过赋予自己什么头衔吗
Certainly not Albert, Sir. Too Germanic.
当然不能是阿尔伯特  阁下  太德国化了
What about George?
乔治怎么样
After your father?
用你父亲的头衔
George the sixth.
乔治六世
It has rather a nice continuity to it,
是个不错的传承
don't you think?
你不觉得吗
David! Thank God.
大卫  谢天谢地
You look exhausted!
你看起来很累坏了
How are you bearing up?
你还撑得住吗
Bertie. The decision's been made, I...
博迪  我已经决定了
I am going.
我要退位
I cannot accept that.
我无法接受
You are in no condition to make that decision.
你无论如何都不该做此决定
I'm afraid there's no other way.
恐怕没有别的办法
I must marry her.
我要娶她
My mind's made up. I'm... sorry.
我已经决定了  抱歉
That's a terrible thing to hear.
真是个糟糕的消息
David, nobody wants that. I least of all.
大卫  没人想你这么做  特别是我
"At long last I am able to say, a few words of my own.
终于  我可以说点自己的话
我于1936年12月10日签字证明
爱德华签署于景观台城堡
I have never wanted to withhold anything,
我从来没有想要隐瞒什么
but until now,
但在此之前
it has not been constitutionally possible for me to speak.
根据宪法我不能发表任何讲话
A few hours ago I discharged my last duty...
几个小时之前  我卸下了
as King and Emperor.
作为一个国王和君主最后职责
And now that I have been succeeded by my brother, the Duke of York
现在  将由我的弟弟约克公爵继位
my first words must be to declare my allegiance to him.
首先我表明对他效忠
This I do with all my heart.
全心全意忠顺
You all know the reasons
相信你们都知道
which have impelled me to renounce the throne.
我宣布放弃王位的原因
But you must believe me, when I tell you
但是请你们相信我接下来的话
I have found it impossible to carry the
如果没有我心爱女人的支持
heavy burden of responsibility and to discharge my duties..
我无法承担如此重任
as King as I would wish to do...
也无法如我所愿的
without the help and support of the woman I love.
卸除作为国王的职责
And I want you to know.
同时  我希望你们知道
This decision has been made less difficult to me...
出于对我弟弟的了解
by the sure knowledge that my brother,
这个决定做的并不艰难
with his long training in the public affairs of this country...
我弟弟一直致力于国家事务管理
and with his fine qualities...
加上他的优秀品质
will be able to take my place forth with...
必然能够即刻继位
without interruption or injury...
不会让国家的前途和发展
to the life and progress of the empire."
受到任何的阻碍或伤害
登基会议
圣詹姆斯宫
1936年12月21日
I meet you at today...
我  在今天
in circumstances which are...
在此情况下  和你们会面
I'm sure you will love it.
我保证你们会喜欢的
Thank you darling, saddles, Margret.
谢谢宝贝  马鞍给我  玛格丽特
- Yes mom. - Good boy.
- 好的  妈妈  - 乖孩子
- 妈妈这是威尔逊马鞍  - 谢谢你
- Mama, here’s the Wilson saddle - Thank you.
别担心  我们一会就喂你吃东西
Don’t worry, we’ll get you food in a minute
Mama, will we have space for our horses in our new home?
妈妈  新家里有地方放小马吗
Of course we will, darling, we'll have a palace of rooms.
当然有  小宝贝  宫殿里有很多房间
Curtsey.
屈膝礼
Your Majesty.
陛下
How was it?
登基怎么样
I'm trying to familiarise myself with what a state paper looks like.
我在努力熟悉公文
A despatch from Mr Baldwin which I don't understand a word of.
鲍德温先生来的信件  我一个字都没看懂
David's finances.
大卫的财务状况
The Christmas... broadcast.
圣诞演说
I think that might be a mistake.
我觉得这是个错误
Don't worry about that.
别担心了
Plans for the Coronation
还有加冕典礼计划
I think that's an even bigger mistake.
这或许是个更大的错误
I'm not a King.
我不是国王
I'm a naval officer. That's all I know.
我是海军军官  只知道怎么做海军军官
I'm not here. I'm not a King.
我不属于这里  我不是国王
I'm sorry.
对不起
Please, please.
别  别这样
Oh, dear. Dear, dear man.
亲爱的  亲爱的
You know...
你知道吗
I refused your first two marriage proposals,
我两次拒绝你的求婚
not because I didn't love you,
不是因为我不爱你
but because I couldn't bear the idea of a Royal life.
而是因为我不能忍受皇室的生活
Couldn't bear the idea of a life of tours and public duties,
不能忍受四处出访和公共责任
a life that no longer was really to be my own.
生活不再属于我们自己
But then I thought...
不过后来我想
he stammers so beautifully...
他是结巴太好了
they'll leave us alone.
大家会放过我们
支持国王  上帝保佑他
Waiting for a king to apologize, one can wait rather a long wait.
等国王来道歉  那要等很久
I'm afraid we're slightly late.
恐怕我们迟到了一会
This is home.
这就是我家
Myrtle's at bridge.
莫特尔去打桥牌了
I've made sure the boys are out.
我让孩子们都出去
It's lovely.
太好了
Absolutely lovely.
非常好
May I sit down?
我能坐这吗
Yes, of course.
当然可以
Would you like some tea, Ma'am?
喝点茶吧  夫人
Yes. I'll help myself.
好的  我自己来就行
Off you go...
你们聊吧
Or must I knock your heads together?
还是需要我强迫你们
Here's your shilling,
这是我欠你的一先令
I... I understand...
我  我明白
what you were trying to say, Logue.
你之前的意思了  罗格
I went about it the wrong way.
我做错了
I'm sorry.
抱歉
So, here I am.
所以  我来了
Is the nation ready for two...
全国准备好
minutes of radio silence?
听我的两分钟无声广播了吗
Every stammerer always fears they will fall back to square one.
所有结巴都害怕自己又回到原点
I don't let that happen.
我不会让这个情况发生的
If I fail in my duty...
如果我做的不好
David could come back.
大卫就会回来
I've seen the placard.
我看到那些布告了
"God save our... King."
天佑吾王
They don't mean me.
他们指的不是我
Every other monarch in history
历史上每一位君主的继任
succeeded someone who was dead, or just about to be.
都是在前任去世或者命不久矣的情况下
My predecessor is not only alive, but very much so.
而我的前任不仅活着  还活得很好
What a bloody mess!
真是一团糟
I can't even give them a Christmas Speech.
我甚至不能发表一次圣诞演说
Like your Dad used to do?
像您父亲曾经那样
Precisely.
没错
He's not here anymore.
他已经不在了
Yes he is. He's on that shilling I gave you.
不  他还在  就在我给你的一先令上
Easy enough to give away.
随便都能送人
You don't have to carry him around in your pocket.
您不用总带着他的影子
Or your brother.
或者你哥哥的影子
You don't need to be afraid of
您无需害怕那些
the things as you were afraid of when you were five.
您五岁时候害怕的东西
You're very much your own man, Bertie.
您已经独立自主  博迪
Am I?
是吗
Your face is next, mate.
你的脸会印在下一批硬币上  哥们
Lionel?
莱昂纳尔
Myrtle!
莫特尔
- Is it alright? - Yes.
- 没事吧  - 没事
Bertie, come here.
博迪  过来
- Are you alright, Logue? - Yes.
- 你还好吧  罗格  - 还好
- Shall we go through? - Trust me. It's important.
- 要出去吗  - 相信我  这很重要
What is it?
怎么了
- Your... Your... - It's your Majesty? The first time.
- 陛  陛  - 第一次叫陛下就好
After that, it's Ma'am. As in Ham, not Malm as in Palm.
之后可以叫夫人  别读错了
I haven't told her about us.
我没跟她讲过我们的事
Sit down, relax.
先坐下  放松
I'm told your husband calls my husband Bertie
你丈夫叫我丈夫博迪
and my husband calls your husband Lionel.
而我丈夫叫你丈夫莱昂纳尔
I trust you won't call me Liz.
我想你应该不会叫我莉斯
Your Majesty, you may call me Mrs Logue, Ma'am.
陛下  你可以叫我罗格夫人
Very nice to meet you, Mrs Logue.
见到你很高兴  罗格夫人
Logue, we can't stand here all day.
罗格  我们不能一直站这
Yes we can. Look, I need to wait for the right moment.
我们可以的  我得等个合适的时候
Logue, you're being a coward!
罗格你这样像胆小鬼
You're damn right.
你说的没错
Get out there, man!
出去吧  伙计
Hello, Myrtle darling!
嗨  亲爱的莫特尔
You're early.
你回来早了
I believe you two have met!
我相信你们已经见过面了
But I didn't think, you know...
但是  我想你应该还没见过
King George the Sixth.
国王乔治六世
It's very nice to meet you.
很高兴见到你
Will their Majesties be staying to dinner?
陛下们要留下吃晚饭吗
We would love to, such a treat, but alas...
我们也想留下来  谢谢你的好意
a previous engagement. What a pitty.
但是有约在身  真遗憾
- Archbishop. - Welcome, your Majesty.
- 主教大人  - 欢迎您  陛下
What a glorious tranformation, Sir.
多么壮观的改造  阁下
I hope you'll forgive us if we continue our preparations.
请允许我们继续准备
And now you will allow me to guide you through the ceremony.
现在请允许我为您介绍仪式的过程
We begin of course at the West door, then into the nave.
我们从西门进来  然后到中殿
I see you all your
我听说您所有讲话
pronouncements are to be broadcast, Archbishop.
都会被广播  主教大人
Ah, yes, wireless is indeed a Pandora's Box.
是的  无线电就像潘多拉的盒子
I'm afraid I also have to permit the newsreel cameras.
我恐怕还得批准新闻摄影的拍摄
The product of which I shall personally edit.
我会亲自监督剪辑的
Without momentary hesitation.
真是毫不犹豫
This is Doctor Logue of Harley Street.
这是哈里大街的罗格医生
He's my speech therapist.
他是我的语言治疗师
- Your Grace. - Had I known
- 大人  - 如果知道
that Your Majesty was seeking assistance
陛下您在寻医
I should've made my own recommendation.
我一定会亲自给您推荐人选的
Dr. Logue...
罗格医生
will be attending the Coronation.
会  会出席加冕礼
Well of course I shall speak with the Dean,
我可以去跟教长说一下
but it was extremely difficult.
但会很困难
I should like the Doctor to be seated in the King's Box.
我想让他坐到国王的包厢里
But members of your Family will be seated there, Sir.
但那是给您的家人准备的  阁下
That is why it's suitable.
这正是那里合适的原因
And now, if you don't mind Your Grace,
大人如果你不介意的话
we need the premises.
我们需要场地准备
My dear fellow, this is Westminster Abbey!
老兄  这可是威斯敏斯特教堂
The Church must prepare his Majesty.
教堂必须为陛下准备
My preparations are equalized in important
我的准备也一样重要
With complete privacy, if you don't mind.
如果你不介意的话  最好清场
Those are my wishes, Your Grace.
我也希望这样  大人
I shall place the Abbey at Your majesty's disposal...
今晚教堂就交由陛下使用
this evening. Your Majesty.
容我告退  陛下
I can't believe I'm walking on...
我不敢相信我正走在
Chaucer and Handel and Dickens.
乔叟  韩德尔和狄更斯的墓上
Everything alright? Let's get cracking.
准备好了吗  我们开始吧
I'm not here to rehearse, Doctor Logue.
我不是来这彩排的  罗格医生
Call me Lionel.
叫我莱昂纳尔
True, you... never... called yourself "Doctor".
是啊  你一直  都不管自己叫医生
I did that... for you.
是我这么叫你
No training, no... diploma, no... qualifications.
没有培训  没有文凭  没有资质
Just a... great deal of nerve.
只有一身的胆量
The star chamber inquisition, is it?
这是秘密审问吗
You asked trust. And... total equality.
你要求信任  和充分的平等
Bertie, I heard you at Wembley.
博迪  我听了你在温布利的演讲
I was there.
我当时在场
My son Laurie said dad,
我的儿子劳里说  爸爸
do you think you could help that poor man?
你能不能帮帮这个可怜人
What, as a failed actor!?
怎么帮  就凭一个失败的演员
It's true, I'm not a doctor,
这是事实  我不是一个医生
and yes I acted a bit,
而且  我确实当过一阵演员
Well I recited in pubs and taught elocution in schools.
我在俱乐部朗诵  在学校教演讲
When the Great War came,
当大战来临
all our Soldiers were returning straight from the front,
我们的士兵从前线回来
a lot of them shell- shocked,
很多人得了炮弹休克症
unable to speak
无法开口说话
somebody said, Lionel, you're very good at all this speech stuff.
有人跟我说  莱昂纳尔  你这么会演讲
Do you think you can possibly help these poor buggers?
你能帮帮这些可怜的人吗
I did muscle therapy, exercise, relaxation,
我做了肌肉治疗练习放松
but I knew I had to go deeper.
但是我知道要治好还需要更多
These poor young blokes had cried out in fear,
这些可怜的年轻人害怕的大叫
no- one was listening to them.
却没有人倾听
My job was to give them faith in their own voice
我的工作就是让他们相信自己的声音
and let them know that a friend was listening.
让他们知道有个朋友在用心倾听
That must ring a few bells with you, Bertie.
博迪  这一定让你想到自己
You give a very noble account of yourself.
你说得自己真高尚
Make inquiries. It's all true.
你去打听  这都是事实
Inquiries have been made!
我都打听过了
You have no idea who I have breathing down my neck?
你不知道多少人在找我的麻烦
I vouched for you
我为你做担保
and you have no... credentials.
可你却连文凭都没有
But lots of success!
可我成功治好了很多人
I can't show you certificate...
我拿不出证书给你看
there was no training then.
那时没有什么培训机构
Everything I know I know from experience,
我会的一切都来自于经验
and that war... was some experience.
是那场战争  给我的经验
My plaque says, "L.Logue, Speech Defects."
我的牌子上写的是  L· 罗格  治疗言语缺陷
No Dr., there are no letters after my name.
没有医生两个字
Lock me in the Tower.
把我关进监狱好了
I would if I could!
如果可以我早就关了
- On what charge? - Fraud!
- 以什么罪名  - 欺诈罪
With war looming,
战争一触即发
you've saddled this nation with a voiceless King.
你让一个不能说话的国王坐上王位
You destroyed the happiness of my family.
你毁了我的家庭幸福
All for the sake of ensnaring a star...
所有这一切都是为了欺骗
patient you couldn't possibly hope to assist!
一个你根本就无法救治的明星病人
It'll be like mad... King George the Third,
就像疯子国王乔治三世
there'll be mad King George the stammerer...
我就是口吃的疯子国王乔治
who let his people down so badly in their hour of need!
在人民最需要的时候让他们失望
What're you doing?
你这是干什么
Get up! You can't sit there! Get up!
起来  你不能坐在这儿  快起来
Why not? It's a chair.
为什么不能  这就是把椅子
No, that's not a chair, that is... that is...
不  那不只是一把椅子  那是  那是
That is Saint Edward's Chair!
那是圣爱德华的王座
People have carved their names on it.
有人随便在上面刻了自己的名字
That chair is the seat on which every King and Queen.
这把椅子是让历任国王和女王
It's held in a place by a large rock!
下面还有块大石头
That's the Stone of Scone yard,
那是来自斯昆的石头
- you are trivialising everything. - You believe such bollocks.
- 你亵渎一切  - 你相信这套吗
You're trivialising everything!
你亵渎一切
I don't care how many royal...
我可不在乎有多少...
- Listen to me. Listen to me! - arse have sat in this chair.
- 听我说  听我说  - 皇族蠢货坐在这椅子上
- Listen to me! - Listen to you? By what right?
- 听我说  - 听你说  凭什么
By the divine right, if you must! I'm your King!!!
神授王权  我是你的国王
No you're not! You told me so yourself.
不  你不是  你自己告诉过我
You said you didn't want it.
你说过你并不想做国王
Why should I waste my time listening to you?
那我为什么还要浪费时间听你说话
Because I have a right to be heard!
因为我有权被倾听
- Heard as what? - I HAVE A VOICE!
- 听什么  - 听我说话
Yes you do.
没错
You have such a perservance,
你有毅力
Bertie, you're the bravest man I know.
博迪  你是我见过的最勇敢的人
And you'll make a bloody good king.
你会成为一个非常好的国王
What on earth's going on, Sir?
这到底是怎么了  陛下
It's quite alright, Archbishop.
一切正常  主教大人
Mr Logue, you must know
罗格先生  我要告诉你
that I found a replacement English specialist
我已经找了一个非常有资质的
with impeccable credentials.
英国专家来替代你
Hence, your services will no longer be required.
你的工作即将结束
I'm sorry?
你说什么
Your Majesty's function is to consult and be advised.
陛下的工作是咨询并听取建议
And you didn't consult, but you've just been advised.
而您没有咨询  但刚得到建议
Now I advise you:
我来给你提个建议
In this personal matter I will make my own decision.
在这  种私人问题上  我会自己做决定
My concern is for the head upon which I must place the crown.
我是为加冕国王的安危着想
I appreciate that Archbshop, but it's my head!
我很感激  主教大人  但这是我自己的事情
Your humble servant.
恕我告退
Thank you Bertie.
谢谢  博迪
Shall we rehearse? Come on upon your purge.
我们排练吧  坐在您的位子上
Now when you and Elizabeth enter through the West door,
当您和伊丽莎白从西门进来之后
you'll be greeted by the hymn "I was glad when they said onto me"
您将听到赞歌  "我很高兴他们对我说"
Actually you won't be that glad,
其实您也没那么高兴
because they sing it for a very long time.
因为他们会在那里唱很久
Then your friend
然后  你的朋友
the Archbishop will ponce up the stairs toward you
主教大人会面向你走上台阶
and say "Sir, is Your Majesty willing to take The oath"
说  "陛下  您愿意宣誓吗"
- "I am willing" - Course you are!
- "我愿意"  - 你当然愿意
I'm gonna see what it sounds like in the cheap seats
我得去最后面的位子听下效果
so even your old nanny can hear.
保证连您的老保姆也能听到
"Will you govern your peoples of Great Britain, Ireland, Canada,
"您愿意根据当地习俗统治不列颠  爱尔兰
Australia and New Zealand according to their lands and customs"
加拿大  澳大利亚  以及新西兰的人民吗"
"I solemnly promise so do so."
"我在此庄严承诺"
Louder! I can't hear you up the back.
大点声  我在后面听不到
"I solemnly promise so do so."
"我在此庄严承诺"
Very good!
很好
"Will you to your power cause Law and Justice, in Mercy,
您愿意以仁爱之心用法律和公正的判断
to be executed in all your judgements?"
来行使您的权利吗
"I will." "I WILL!"
"我愿意"  "我愿意"
Then there's a very long bit about upholding the faith,
之后会有很长一段是关于坚持信念的
goes on, rubbish, rubbish, rubbish. To which you finally say...
继续的也是废话  废话  废话  直到你最后说
"The things which I have... here before promised,
"我在这里所承诺的事
I will perform and keep."
我会一如既往的履行"
So help me God
上帝保佑
And that's all you'll say. Four short responses,
你要说的就是这些  只有四句
kiss the book and sign the oath and you're King.
亲吻那本书  在誓约上签字  你就是国王了
Easy.
很简单
You nearly crowned him backwards Archbishop!
您差点把王冠戴反了  主教大人
Someone had removed the thread marking the back of the Crown, Sir.
有人把标志王冠反面的线弄掉了  陛下
Try not lose the thread, Archbishop.
别把线弄掉  主教大人
Archbishop, we're missing Papa.
主教先生  我们看不到爸爸了
Very good, very good. Archbishop.
非常好  非常好  主教大人
Well, I hope Your Majesties are thrilled with the result.
我希望国王和王后陛下对结果满意
You could switch that machine off now.
现在你可以把机器关掉了
No, wait, keep going.
不要  等等  继续放
Do have a seat, Archbishop.
请坐下吧  主教大人
Papa? Papa, what's he saying?
爸爸  爸爸  他在说什么
I don't know, but he seems to be saying it rather well.
不知道  但他似乎说的很好
Sir, I have asked to see you today...
陛下  我今天来见您
in order to tender my resignation as Prime Minister.
是为了向您辞去首相的职务
I am so sorry to hear that, Mr Baldwin.
听你这么说我很难过  鲍德温先生
Neville Chamberlain will take my place as Prime Minister.
内维尔·张伯伦会接替首相之职
It's a matter of principal. I was mistaken.
我在一个重大问题上做了错误的决定
I have found it impossible to believe...
很难想像  这个世界上
that there is any man in the world...
竟然有像希特勒这样
so lacking in moral feeling as Hitler,
如此缺乏道德感
but the world may be hurled for...
而这个世界也很可能会
a second time into the abyss of destructive War.
再次陷入战争灾难的深渊
Churchill was right all along.
一直以来丘吉尔都是对的
This was always Hitler's intention.
这就是希特勒的野心
I am many very sorry to leave you in this great time of crisis.
在这危急时刻离开您  我感到很抱歉
I am very much afraid Sir,
国王陛下  我很担心
that your greatest test is yet to come.
您将面临最大的考验
I am speaking to you from the cabinet room...
我在唐宁街10号的内阁会议室
at 10 Downing Street.
发表广播(1939年9月3日)
This morning the British Ambassador in Berlin...
今天早晨  英国驻柏林大使
handed the German Government a final note...
提交了一份德国政府的最后声明
stating that unless we heard from them by 11 oclock,
如果我们在11点之前没有得到知会
that they were prepared at once...
既是表示德国已经做好准备
to withdraw their troops from Poland,
立即从波兰撤军
a state of war would exist between us.
德英两国随即进入战争状态
I have to tell you now
我要告诉你们的是
that no such undertaking has been received,
我们并未收到任何知会
and that consequently, this country is at war with Germany.
因此  德英两国已经进入战争状态
At last Sir, here is your speech.
最后  陛下  这是您的演讲稿
You are on air at six.
6点开始直播
I've timed it at just under nine minutes.
时间不超过9分钟
The wording is fully approved.
措辞经过充分推敲
The Prime Minister will be joining you for the broadcast
首相先生也将在广播中发表演说
which will go out live across the Nation,
这次广播将在全国
the Empire and to our Armed Forces.
整个帝国及军队播放
Get Logue here immediately.
马上把罗格叫过来
- There's the barrage balloons. - Yes.
- 那是防空气球  - 是呀
- They got them up there quickly. - Yeah.
- 他们动作倒是挺快  - 是啊
Should we pull over and find shelter?
我们是不是停车找掩体躲避
No, go straight on. We'll be alright
不  继续开  没事的
- Yes. Sir? - Lionel Logue.
- 您好  先生  - 我是莱昂纳尔·罗格
Major Hartley's expecting me. This is my son Laury.
哈特利大人正在等我  这是我的儿子劳里
- Thank you, Laurie. - Good luck, Dad.
- 谢谢  劳里  - 一切顺利  爸爸
- The King's Speech. - Thank you, Sir.
- 这是国王的演讲稿  - 谢谢  先生
We have about forty minutes to the broadcast.
现在离直播还有大约40分钟
Thank you very much. Thank you.
非常感谢  谢谢
"there may be dark days ahead, and..."
"我们前方也许是黑暗"
Try again.
再来一次
"there may be dark days ahead, and..."
"我们前方也许是黑暗"
Turn the hesitations into pauses...
在卡住的地方停顿
and say to yourself, "God save the King."
然后自言自语说  天佑吾王
I say that continuously, but apparently no one's listening.
这句话我经常说  可明显没人听
Long pauses are good. They add solemnity to great occasions.
长的停顿很好  在重大场合更显庄重
Then I'm the solemnest king who ever lived.
那我就是最为庄重的国王
You know, if I am to be King, where is my power?
如果我是国王  权利何在
Can I... Can I reform a government?
我能  我能重组内阁吗
Can I... Can I... levy a tax? Declare a war? No.
我能  我能征税吗  能宣战吗  不能
Yet I am the seat of all authority. Why?
而我是所有职权的代表  为什么
Because the Nation believes that when I... I speak, I speak for them.
因为民众相信我是为了他们讲话
But I cannot speak!
但我却不善于讲话
Let's take it all again from the top.
我们从头再来一遍
"In this grave hour"
从"在这一庄严时刻"开始
In this grave hour... Fuck, fuck, fuck.
在这一庄严时刻  操  操  操
perhaps the most fateful in our history... Bugger, shit, shit.
也许是我们有史以来最生死攸关的时刻  混蛋  日  日
I send to every household of my...
我要向所有家庭
You see, "P" is always difficult, even when I'm singing.
就算我唱着说  "人"也总是很难发音
Bounce on to it. "A peoples."
遇到"人"的时候用"一个人"代替
- Not people. - A people.
- 而不是"人"  - 一个人
Household of my peoples both at home...
大英人民的所有家庭  无论是在国内
- and overseas. - Beautiful.
- 还是海外  - 很好
this message, doo- dah day.
传达这一消息  啦啦啦
spoken with the same depth of feeling. Doo- dah day...
怀着同样的深刻情感  啦啦啦
for each one of you as if I were able to... Shit, fuck, bugger!
对你们每个人说  就好像我在  日  操  混蛋
cross your threshold and speak to you...
和你们面对面交流
In your head, now. "I have a right to be bloody well heard."
你要在脑子里想  我有权力要你们都听到
Bloody well heard, bloody well heard, bloody well heard myself!
都听到  都听到  都听到我说话
Now, waltz. Move. Get continuous movement.
来段华尔兹  动起来  动作流畅
For the second time in the lives of most of us we are at...
对大多数人来说  在有生之年  我们第二次...
- "We are," Take a pause. - Lionel, I can't do this.
- "我们"要停顿一下  - 莱昂纳尔  我做不来
Bertie, you can do it.
博迪  你可以的
- Have a look at the last paragraph. - Bertie, it's time.
- 再看一下最后一段  - 博迪  时间到了
- Archbishop. - Your Majesty.
- 主教大人  - 国王陛下
A great moment, Sir.
伟大的时刻  陛下
- Prime Minister. - Your Majesty.
- 首相  - 国王陛下
Nice to see you... again so soon.
我们又见面了  真快
Good of you to be here.
你能来很好
I'm sure you've had rather a busy day.
我相信你刚度过了繁忙的一天
Let's hope we have no more
希望我们不会再被那些
interruptions from those damned sirens, Sir.
该死的警报声打断  阁下
Or the wretched dogs.
或者那些可怜的小狗们
Congrat... Congratulations. First Lord of the Admiralty.
恭喜你荣任海军大臣
Your Majesty.
谢谢国王陛下
The long... walk.
很长...  一段路
Good luck, Sir.
一切顺利  陛下
I, too, dread this apparatus.
我也害怕这种仪器
Had a speech impediment myself, you know.
您知道吗  我也曾口吃
- I didn't. - Family secret. Tongue- tied.
- 没听说过  - 家族秘密  舌头打结
An operation was considered to be too dangerous.
手术风险很大
I eventually made an asset of it.
最终我把它变成长处了
- Thank you, Mr Churchill. - Sir.
- 谢谢  丘吉尔先生  - 陛下请
Darling.
亲爱的
How long, Logue?
还有多久  罗格
Just under three minutes, Sir.
不到3分钟  陛下
- Mr Wood. - Good luck, Your Majesty.
- 伍德先生  - 好运  陛下
Mr Wood.
伍德先生
You'll be decorated, Logue.
你会被授予奖章  罗格
I made it cosy.
拿来当杯垫
Some fresh air.
来点新鲜空气
There you are, Darling.
来吧  亲爱的
I'm thistle sifter, I've a sieve
吃葡萄不吐葡萄皮
of sifted thistles and a sieve on unsifted thistles.
不吃葡萄倒吐葡萄皮
I've a sieve of sifted thistles
吃葡萄不吐葡萄皮
and a sieve on unsifted thistles, because I'm...
不吃葡萄倒吐葡萄皮
Bertie, darling, make sure it's not switched on!
博迪  亲爱的  别忘了开关
Remember the red light will blink four times
记住红灯闪烁4次之后
and then I've asked them to turn it off,
我会叫他们关灯
because we don't want that
因为不想
evil eye staring at you all the way through.
让那只邪恶的眼睛一直盯着你
One minute, sir.
还有1分钟  陛下
I am sure you will be splendid.
我肯定你会做得非常好
Fourty seconds, Sir.
40秒  陛下
Logue, however this turns out,
罗格 不管结果如何
I don't know how to thank you for what you've done.
我都不知道该如何感谢你
Knighthood?
授爵行吗
Twenty seconds.
20秒
Forget everything else and just say it to me.
抛开一切  只要对着我说话就好
Say it to me, as a friend.
对着我说  就像对朋友说
In this grave hour,
在这一庄严时刻
perhaps the most fateful in our history,
也许是我们有史以来生死攸关的时刻
I send to every household of my peoples,
我要向大英人民的每个家庭
both at home...
无论是在国内
and overseas,
还是海外
this message...
传达这一消息
spoken with the same depth of feeling...
和你们一样
for each one of you...
怀着同样深刻的感受
as if I were able to cross your threshold...
就好像我在和你们
and speak to you myself.
面对面交谈
For the second time in the lives of most of us,
对我们大多数人来说  有生之年
we are at... at war.
我们再一次面临  面临战争
Over and over again,
一次有一次
we have tried to find...
我们竭尽全力
a peaceful way out of the differences between ourselves...
想为我们和那些如今成为敌人的人之间的差异
and those who are now our enemies.
找到和平的解决办法
But it has been in vain.
但终是突然
We have been forced into a conflict.
我们被迫面临冲突
For we are called, to meet the challenge of a principle
因为我们是被号召去挑战一种信条
which, if it were to prevail,
这种信条如果获胜
would be fatal to any civilized order...
将是对全世界文明秩序的
in the world.
致命打击
Such a principle,
这种信条
stripped of all disguise,
剥除所有伪装
is surely the mere...
无疑是一种简单的
primitive doctrine that might is right.
原始信条  那就是强权即真理
For the sake of all that we ourselves hold dear,
为了我们所珍惜的一切
it is unthinkable that we should refuse to meet the challenge.
毫无疑问  我们不应拒绝迎接这种挑战
It is to this high purpose that I now call...
为了这个崇高的目标  在此
my people at home and my peoples across the seas,
我号召海内外所有的大英臣民
who will make our cause their own.
将我们事业当作自己的事业
I ask them to stand calm and firm,
请你们保持镇静和坚定
and united in this time of trial.
在此危难之时团结一致
The task will be hard.
任务十分艰巨
There may be dark days ahead,
我们前方也许是黑暗
and war can no longer be confined to the battlefield.
而战争也将不再局限于战场
But we can only do the right as we see the right...
但我们只能做我们认为正确的事情
and reverently commit our cause to God.
并向上帝虔诚祈祷
If one and all we keep resolutely faithful to it,
如果我们所有人都能坚定信念
then, with God's help,
那么  有上帝的庇佑
we shall prevail.
我们将取得胜利
Very good, Bertie.
非常好  博迪
You still stammered on the "w"?
你说"和"还是有点结巴
Had to throw in a few so they knew it was me.
总得结巴几下  他们才知道是我
Congratulations, your Majesty. A true broadcaster.
恭喜您  国王陛下  一次真正的广播
Thank you, Mr Wood.
谢谢  伍德先生
Congratulations, your Majesty.
恭喜您  国王陛下
- Congratulations, your Majesty. - Thank you.
- 恭喜您  陛下  - 谢谢
Ready.
好了
- Good? - Perfect.
- 行吗  - 很好
Your first war time speech. Congratulations.
你的首次战争演讲  恭喜
Expect I shall have to do a great deal more.
我还应做的更好
Thank you, Logue.
谢谢你  罗格
Well done, my friend.
干得好  我的朋友
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢谢您  国王陛下
I knew you'd be good.
我知道你行的
Thank you, Lionel.
谢谢你  莱昂纳尔
Onwards?
继续吧
Congratulations, Sir.
恭喜您  陛下
Almost did it better than myself, Sir.
您做得比我还好  陛下
Your Majesty, I'm speechless.
国王陛下  您让我难以言表
Congratulations, Sir.
恭喜您  陛下
Gentlemen.
先生们
Congratulations, your Majesty.
恭喜您  国王陛下
So how was Papa, Elizabeth?
你觉得爸爸怎么样  伊丽莎吧
Halting at first, but you got much better Papa.
开始有些吞吐  但已经很好了  爸爸
Bless you.
亲一个
- And how about you, Margaret? - You were just splendid, Papa.
- 你觉得呢  玛格丽特  - 真是太精彩了  爸爸
Of course I was.
那当然了
We all ready?
都准备好了吗
Come on girls.
来吧姑娘们
1944年
乔治六世国王为莱昂纳尔·罗格授予了英国皇家维多利亚勋章
这是为感谢为君主个人服务而特别设立的唯一勋章
此后国王的每一次战争演讲都有莱昂纳尔陪同
通过广播  乔治六世国王成为国家抵抗的象征
莱昂纳尔和博迪在有生之年一直保持友谊
谢谢观赏
-=圣城家园 CnSCG 荣誉出品=-
hd.cnscg.com